A Finding Aid to the Gene Davis Papers, 1920-2000, bulk 1942-1990, in the Archives of American Art AAA.davigene
Archives of American Art
- Photographs, 1920-2000; Series 7; 3.8 Linear feet Boxes 11-15, 17, OV 19
  - Photographs of Artwork, Exhibition Views (Box 15)
    - Guggenheim Museum, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Jefferson Place Gallery, 1961; 1967; Black and white prints and color slides (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Max Protetch Gallery, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - ArtPark, Niagara, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Milwaukee Art Museum, circa 1980; Includes 1 color print (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Muscarelle Museum of Art, Sun Sonata, 1983; Color prints (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Nova Scotia College of Art and Design, circa 1970 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Osuna Art Gallery, circa 1980-1990; Color prints and negatives (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Paris Art Fair, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - San Francisco Art Museum, circa 1966 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Smithsonian National Museum of American Art, 1987; 4 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 15, Folder 23-24)
      Also contains 1 color snapshot
    - Tate Gallery, circa 1970 (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - University of Nebraska, Sheldon Art Gallery, circa 1973 (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - Walker Art Center, 1978; Contains color prints; See also disassembled photograph album 3 (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Washington Gallery of Modern Art, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified Exhibitions, circa 1968-1983; Contains color prints, polaroids, and slides (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - Oversized Photographs from Box 12, folder 27 (Box 17)
  - Oversized Photographs from Box 13, folder 42 (Box 17)
  - Oversized Photographs from Box 14, folder 21 (Box 17)
  - Oversized Photographs from Box 14, folder 32 (Box 17)
  - Oversized Photographs from Box 12, folder 30 (Box 20)
- Artwork, bulk 1968-1971; 1930-1985; Series 8; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 15-16, 18
  Artwork includes a wide variety of material, including conceptual art, photographs, drawings, and moving images. Conceptual works include “The Artist’s Fingerprints Except for One which belongs to someone else,” created by Davis, and documentation of the 1969 “Giveaway,” a collaboration between Davis, Ed McGowin, and Douglas Davis. Records related to the “Giveaway” include printed artist statements from Douglas Davis, Ed McGowin, and Gene Davis, and photocopied correspondence and notes documenting the event. Artworks by others include a conceptual writing piece by Juan Downey, and documentation of a happening by Wendy Stern, which includes witnessing “Air Displacement,” a happening performed by Gene Davis in 1970.
  Sketches appear to be ideas for stripe paintings, some with detailed notes written by Davis. Art photographs include a range of compositional experiments and appear to have been taken by Davis. Drawings are mainly informal drawings of Davis made by others. A Handmade sign reading “Allan Kapprow [sic] Happening” is also found.
  Moving images include both film and video, with two finished works and 13 super 8 film reels which appear to be Davis’s initial experiments with the medium. “Patricia” is a black and white 16mm film of a closely composed face of a woman changing facial expressions. Unlike the super 8 films, “Patricia” has an identifying title frame and appears to be a finished work. “Video Puzzle” documents a happening in a gallery in 1971 and may be the only surviving video from Davis’s period of experimentation with video art.
  The super 8 films contain a variety of content. Four of the reels contain static, rhythmic compositions of Davis’s stripe paintings. Two of the reels indicate they were made in a class setting and contain compositions of interior lighting and close ups of faces. Another two reels are labeled “Masks, Corcoran,” and contain static shots of Davis and others posing with handmade masks. Four additional reels contain street footage of kids in a park, young people gathered outside, Davis’s dogs, and the exterior of his Pennsylvania Avenue studio.
  Still images from additional video art by Davis videos are found in series 7, Photographs. Additional information about the Giveaway event is found in series 3, Correspondence, series 5, Writings, and series 7, Photographs. Additional moving images are found in series 1, Biographical Materials, series 4, Business and Estate Records, and series 7, Photographs.
  - The Artist’s Fingerprints Except for One Which Belongs to Someone Else, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Giveaway Documentation, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 31)
  - A Novel by Juan Downey, circa 1968 (Box 15, Folder 32)
  - Self Portrait in Washington by Wendy Stern, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 33)
  - Art Photography, circa 1979 (Box 15, Folder 34)
  - Drawings, circa 1930-1968 (Box 15, Folder 35)
  - Handmade Sign for Allan Kaprow Happening, circa 1965 (Box 15, Folder 36)
  - Sketches, circa 1960-1985 (Box 15, Folder 37)
  - Moving Images (Box 15)
    - Patricia, circa 1970; 1 Film reels black and white, silent 16 mm (Box 15, Folder 38)
      Film reel in Box 18
    - Video Puzzle, circa 1971; 1 Videoreels (½ inch) black and white, sound (Box 15, Folder 39)
    - Art Films of Stripe Paintings, 1969; 4 Film reels color, silent; film boxes labeled "stripe paintings" and numbered 1-4 Super 8 mm (Box 15, Folder 40-41)
    - Abstract Compositions from Art Classes, circa 1969; 2 Film reels color, silent; film boxes labeled "film made in class" and "A.V. class" Super 8 mm (Box 15, Folder 42)
    - Davis and Students Posing with Masks, circa 1969; 3 Film reels color, silent; film boxes labeled "Masks, Corcoran" Super 8 mm (Box 15, Folder 43-44)
    - Street Films, circa 1969; 4 Film reels color, silent; film reels and boxes labeled “negro kids, my first film”, “Hippies,” “ants, Old Studio” Super 8 mm (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Unidentified Motion Picture Film, circa 1970; 2 Film reels Unprocessed, exposed film Super 8 mm (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Film Reel of Patricia (Box 18)